<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The 7th Position]]></title>
  <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-03T01:15:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bhousel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bryan Housel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I have my own word]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/17/i-have-my-own-word/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/17/i-have-my-own-word</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/thumbs_down.jpg" width="266" height="400"></p>

<p><strong>be·hou·sel</strong> -
<a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/help/ahd4/pronkey.html">(bĭ-hou &#8216;zəl)</a>
<em>-verb (used with object),</em> <strong>-seled, -sel·ing</strong></p>

<p>Definition:<br/>
To unimpress or underwhelm esp. so as to make obvious to faults or shortcomings:</p>

<p>Usage:<br/>
<em>&#8220;Audiences were behouseled by The Phantom Menace.&#8221;</em></p>

<p>Related forms:<br/>
<strong>be·hou·sel·ment</strong>, <em>noun</em><br/>
<strong>be·hou·sel·ing·ly</strong>, <em>adverb</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the most fun you've ever had programming?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/07/most-fun-had-programming/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/07/most-fun-had-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/floops.jpg" width="452" height="302" title="Floops!" ></p>

<p>During the dot-com bubble in the late &#8217;90s
I worked at a startup company called
<a href="http://www.openworlds.com/">OpenWorlds</a>, just
me and a few other programmers in a small office. 
We were building a toolkit for using
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vrml">VRML</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X3D">X3D</a>, which was
a kind of 3D version of the HTML that powers the world wide web. 
VRML never took off, for
<a href="http://www.softwaredeveloper.com/features/ghosts-in-machine-071207/">many reasons</a>
that seem obvious now, but at the
time people were excited about anything involving the web or 3D graphics.</p>

<p>The best part of the job was traveling to conventions like
<a href="http://www.siggraph.org/">SIGGRAPH</a>
to demo our software with a bunch
of other startup companies. They did this thing called the
<a href="http://www.web3d.org/">Web3D</a> RoundUP where each company had a few
minutes to do a demo, and the audience, served alcohol beforehand, had
noisemakers to let you know how well the demo was going. If you went over
time, they’d shoot you with ping pong ball guns.  There was a lot of last
minute coding going on, and the demos were pretty crashy, but the whole party
atmosphere at the time was loads of fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If there is one thing you learned along the way that you would tell new developers, what would it be?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/06/one-thing-to-tell-new-developers/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/06/one-thing-to-tell-new-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/compass.jpg" width="400" height="266"></p>

<p>To be really successful in this business, you need to be more than just a
programmer.  You need people skills, communication, and empathy.  You need
creativity and curiosity - never stop reading and learning.  You need to be
a critical thinker and a problem solver.</p>

<p>Get out in the world and meet people who are not programmers, and understand
<em>their</em> needs, and build software that <em>they</em> can use.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If you knew then what you know now, would you have started programming?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/05/if-you-know-then-what-you-know-now/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/05/if-you-know-then-what-you-know-now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/electrical_engineering.jpg" width="400" height="266"></p>

<p>Yes! In fact, I majored in Electrical and Computer Engineering in college.
This involved lots of circuit design, robotics, electronics, power systems,
etc. I got a minor in Computer Science almost as an afterthought. But if I
knew then what I know now, I would have majored in Computer Science instead.</p>

<p>Today&#8217;s hardware is complicated stuff, and I realized about halfway through
getting my degree that engineers today are pretty much limited to working on
tiny pieces of big projects. Sure, there was time when a few engineers could
launch a hardware company from their garage, but those days are long gone.
The barrier to entry in the hardware business has increased so much that you
now need to be a big international company, like Sony or Apple, to begin to
think about bringing new hardware to market.</p>

<p>Software has gotten complex too - but creating software is still accessible
to anyone with an idea, a computer, and an internet connection. The tools
that we use to create software are, themselves, other pieces of software that
have evolved to match the demands of this business that we’re in. We have
frameworks and toolkits and libraries (often free!) to handle all those
complicated details for us. Developing software still feels creative and
personal. Once it’s complete, you can show it to people and say, &#8220;I did that.&#8221;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What was your first professional programming gig?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/04/what-was-your-first-programming-gig/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/04/what-was-your-first-programming-gig</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/handshake.jpg" width="400" height="266"></p>

<p>One of the best decisions I made was to go to
<a href="http://www.drexel.edu/">Drexel University</a> for my undergraduate degree,
because they basically require everyone to go on internships. You get your
degree in 5 years, but for the middle three years you alternate between 6
months of class and 6 months of paid internship. Drexel even had a required
class for all freshmen to teach you how to write a resume, how to interview,
how to act at work, etc.</p>

<p>So in 1995, my sophomore year in college, I went to work at my first
internship for a small consulting company called
<a href="http://www.gnostech.com/">Gnostech</a>.
I remember in the interview they asked me:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Do you ever work on programming projects on the side just for fun?<br/>
(&#8220;Yes, I’m working on an online game. I haven’t decided whether it will
be set in medieval times or outer space, so I’m trying to be as generic
as possible.&#8221;)</p></li>
<li><p>Do you know the difference between C and C++?<br/>
(&#8220;Not really, they look the same, but I know in C++ you can change around
how the operators work.&#8221;).</p></li>
</ol>


<p>I guess those answers were good enough for them, so they marked me down as a
&#8220;qualified alternate&#8221; and I somehow got the job.</p>

<p>Gnostech was a typical small company, and they did all kinds of various
computer stuff for other companies in the area - which actually made it a
fantastic place to do an internship. One day I might be installing a network,
another day I’d be soldering components onto circuit boards, another day I was
writing software to test the circuit boards.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What languages have you used since you started programming?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/03/what-languages-have-you-used/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/03/what-languages-have-you-used</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/c_programming_language.jpg" width="246" height="323"></p>

<p>Wow, that’s a long list.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>At my first job, I mostly updated other people’s programs using
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_%28programming_language%29">C</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B">C++</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_basic">Visual Basic</a>, and even a little
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortran">FORTRAN</a>.  I started to learn
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ada_%28programming_language%29">Ada</a>,
because at the time I thought it would be the next big thing.</p>

<p>Throughout college, I actually majored in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrical_engineering">Electrical Engineering</a>,
so we had to learn other kinds of programming languages that most programmers
don’t bother with &#8211; stuff like
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labview">Labview</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maple_%28software%29">Maple</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matlab">MATLAB</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPICE">SPICE</a>, and various
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assembly_language">assembly languages</a>.
In one class, we wrote a traffic light simulator in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vhdl">VHDL</a> and burned that code onto
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FPGA">FPGA</a> chips, then hooked it up to
little red, yellow, and green LEDs on a breadboard.
And I took another fun class where we used
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objective_c">Objective C</a> to get a little Lego
robot to navigate around obstacles without falling off a table. 
I even won a t-shirt for that.</p>

<p>I also got a minor in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_science">Computer Science</a>
and, already knowing C, I was able to skip over a lot of courses.
There were some classes using the more esoteric stuff like
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prolog">Prolog</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scheme_%28programming_language%29">Scheme</a> &#8211;
those courses were fun for me.</p>

<p>For a while I had a job working at a company that sold a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vrml">VRML</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X3D">X3D</a> toolkit built using
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B">C++</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opengl">OpenGL</a>.  The parser library used
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flex_lexical_analyser">Flex</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_bison">Bison</a>, which I count as actual
languages worth knowing.  We also used some
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tcl">Tcl</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_%28programming_language%29">Java</a>, and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javascript">JavaScript</a> there.</p>

<p>I picked up all the usual web stuff along the way, learning
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Html">HTML</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML">XML</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascading_Style_Sheets">CSS</a>, and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javascript">JavaScript</a>.  I also used
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Php">PHP</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perl">Perl</a> for some side projects.</p>

<p>My day job involves building enterprise legal applications.  The
<a href="http://www.lawmanager.com">LawManager</a>
software that I use is written in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CodeGear_Delphi">Delphi</a>, and uses
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vbscript">VBScript</a> as a scripting language.
It also supports an older proprietary scripting language called EvLa,
and I’m probably one of only a handful in the world who knows it. 
The job also requires me to know a lot of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sql">SQL</a>, both Microsoft
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-SQL">T-SQL</a> and Oracle
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PL/SQL">PL/SQL</a> variants.</p>

<p>For a while, I got really interested in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_%28programming_language%29">C#</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASP.NET_MVC_Framework">ASP.NET MVC</a>.</p>

<p>But my current favorite language is
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_%28programming_language%29">Ruby</a>
I&#8217;ve built a few projects in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_on_Rails">Ruby on Rails</a>.</p>

<p>Also, I don’t think you can exist in this business without knowing some
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shell_scripting">shell scripting</a> and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expressions">regular expressions</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What was the first real program you wrote?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/02/what-was-the-first-real-program/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/02/what-was-the-first-real-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/c64_prompt.gif" width="360" height="248"></p>

<p>I remember playing a prank on my dad when I was a little kid. The Commodore 64s
had an overheating issue where sometimes random exclamation marks would start
to appear on the screen. Using the RND, PEEK, and POKE commands, I figured out
how to clear the screen and start putting those &#8216;!&#8217; symbols all over the place.
My dad initially got mad, thinking he would have to return yet another
Commodore 64 to Toys &#8216;R Us or wherever he got it, until I showed him that it
was just some silly program that I wrote.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How did you get started in programming?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/01/how-did-you-get-started-in-programming/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/04/01/how-did-you-get-started-in-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/c64.jpg" width="320" height="203"></p>

<p>Back in the 1980’s, books and magazines would list BASIC programs and you could
type them in line by line and run them yourself.  I remember getting an
&#8220;Artificial Intelligence for the Commodore 64&#8221; book that started out with some
simple classic computer programs, like Tic-Tac-Toe and Towers of Hanoi, and
worked its way up in difficulty to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELIZA">ELIZA</a>.
It took me forever to type in that
<a href="http://www.atariarchives.org/bigcomputergames/showpage.php?page=22">complete Eliza program</a>,
but I remember playing with the program for hours, trying to ask it silly
questions.  For an impressionable little kid, that was pretty powerful stuff, to
be able to type in a complete program and interact with it.</p>

<p>The Commodore 64 had all of these cool peripherals that you could get for it. We
got the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodore_1541">1541 Disk Drive</a> and
started swapping games with friends.  Anyone could copy games and disks, and you
could even punch a hole in the side of the disk to make it double sided.  I
wrote a menu program to load the games from the disks.  If I could go back and
write that program differently, knowing what I know about programming today, I
wouldn’t <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hard_coding">hardcode</a> all the filenames.</p>

<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/tradewars2002.jpg" width="400" height="232"></p>

<p>When I was 12 years old, I borrowed a 300 baud modem from my friend Adam Foxman
and never gave it back.  We both got involved in the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulletin_board_system">BBS scene</a>,
and we did our share of leeching <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warez">warez</a>,
playing
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legend_of_the_Red_Dragon">Legend of the Red Dragon</a>
and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TradeWars_2002">Tradewars</a>, reading the
<a href="http://www.anarchistcookbookz.com/download.html">Anarchist&#8217;s Cookbook</a>,
and all the other fun stuff that went along with the BBS scene at the time.
Basically, everything that has happened to me since 1988 has been somehow Adam’s
fault.</p>

<p>By age 16, I had saved up enough money to buy my own computer, a
brand new Intel 486 DX2/66, PC with a US Robotics Sportster 56k modem, and I
decided to set up my own BBS.  I ran a copy of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WWIV">WWIV</a>, mostly because all the other
friendly sysops in the 215 area code were running it, and we could easily get
the source code (which at the time was C).  I even got connected to WWIVlink so
I could send mail and post messages that would get shuffled around the country.
People used this pre-Internet to trade source code snippets and modifications.</p>

<p>Predictably, one of my favorite mods for WWIV was replacing the normal
chat with that silly Eliza simulation, so that when people would hit &#8216;C&#8217; to chat
with the sysop, they&#8217;d be chatting up Eliza instead.  The mod even put random
delays, typos, and backspaces into the chat.  At the time, many of the people
who could call my BBS were still new to computers and didn&#8217;t catch on that they
were chatting with a bot.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/03/31/about-me/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhousel.github.com/blog/2011/03/31/about-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bhousel.github.com/images/me_winning.jpg" width="480" height="360" title="Winning." ></p>

<p>This photo was taken right after I won second place in my age group at
a local 5k. I was a bit disappointed that they didn&#8217;t rush over
and drape an American flag over my shoulders.</p>

<p>My wife called me a &#8220;tool&#8221; (rightly) and then snapped this photo of me savoring
the sweet metallic taste of almost victory.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
